<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The advantage of a learned education being a sermon preached at the cathedral Church of St. Paul on St. Paul's day 1697/8, before the gentlemen educated at that school, upon the reviving their antient anniversary meeting / by W. Nicholls, D.D.</title>
            <author>Nicholls, William, 1664-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12353834</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12353834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 643:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The advantage of a learned education being a sermon preached at the cathedral Church of St. Paul on St. Paul's day 1697/8, before the gentlemen educated at that school, upon the reviving their antient anniversary meeting / by W. Nicholls, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Nicholls, William, 1664-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Redmayne for Fran. Saunders ..., and Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697/8.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXII, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Education --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ADVANTAGE OF A <hi>Learned Education.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A SERMON Preached at the <hi>Cathedral Church of St.</hi> Paul On St. <hi>PAUL</hi>'s Day 1697/8.</p>
            <p>Before the GENTLEMEN Educated at <hi>That</hi> School, upon the Reviving their Antient Anniverſary Meeting.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Nicholls</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Redmayne</hi> for <hi>Fran. Saunders</hi> at the <hi>New Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and
<hi>Benj. Tooke</hi> at the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in
<hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1697/8.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:2"/>
            <head>To my School-Fellows Bred at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s School.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deareſt Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here Preſent You with a very haſty and a very imperfect Diſcourſe, which I had neither Time nor Books about me to make better; and I can only attribute it to your kind Affection to me, that you have preſſed me to the Publiſhing it. And, ſince it has the Fate to go abroad, pray God it may do ſome Good, and that it may be Read with as much Candor and Affection as you heard it; and then it may poſſibly ſomewhat Advance the Cauſe both of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which it is too much the Faſhion of our Age to deſpiſe. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
               <signed>Your Moſt Faithful Servant and Loving School-fellow W. NICHOLLS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60057:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACT. XXII. III.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I verily am a Man, which am a Jew, born in <hi>Tarſus</hi> a City of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> yet brought up in this City at the Feet of
<hi>Gamaliel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Day is by the Church ſet aſide, to give God thanks for the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Example and bleſſed Labours of that Glorious Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul:</hi> And ſeveral of us are here met together upon another more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account, to thank God Almighty for our ingenuous Education in that School, which bears the Name, and is dedicated to the Honour of that Great Saint. And therefore the better to ſuit my Diſcourſe to both theſe Occaſions, I have choſen theſe Words of that Apoſtle which he ſpoke concerning himſelf. The occaſion was this, as the Hiſtory of the preceding Chapter informs us: When St. <hi>Paul</hi> came to Preach the Goſpel at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> fearing great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment would accrue thereby to their Religion, fancying by miſtake a mighty indignity to be paſſed by him upon their Publick Worſhip, by his having brought <hi>Trophimus</hi> a <hi>Gentile</hi> into the Temple, whom they ſaw he freely converſed <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60057:4"/>with in the Streets, they were preſently all over the City in an Uproar: The tumultuous Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude run inſtantly in Sholes towards the Temple, to know the Truth of this heinous Accuſation, where they find St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preaching; when in a fury they drag him from thence into the Streets, and forthwith ſhut up the Temple Doors: And thus he lay at the mercy of the barbarous Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, which would in a little time have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him, had not the Chief Captain of the Gariſon reſcued him by a Band of Soldiers, which made a ſhift to get him out of the Hands of the Rabble, and carry him Priſoner into the Caſtle; and thither the outragious Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude follow likewiſe; but when St. <hi>Paul</hi> found, he was now got into an advantageous Place for ſpeaking to the People, and whom he ſaw ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aw'd by the Authority of the Captain; he obtained leave to make an Apology to them, for himſelf. There are ſeveral Arguments in this Speech, by which he endeavours to juſtifie his Actions, and to recommend himſelf to their good Opinion, as particularly his Miraculous Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and his former Sincerity and Zeal for the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Worſhip, but that, which I ſhall parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly inſiſt upon, is his being brought up at the Feet of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi> To be brought up at the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60057:4"/>Feet of any one is to be a Scholar, for the
<hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Rabbins were wont to ſit in an Upper Bench, and their Scholars at their Feet; hence came the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Proverb, <hi>happy is the Man that is dirtied by the Feet of the Wiſe,</hi> i. e. has had a literate Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. But <hi>Gamaliel</hi> was a Maſter of greater Fame and Abilities than other Rabbins, he was Preſident of the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and, if I may ſo ſpeak, Doctor of the Chair; a Perſon of whom the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Books do at this time ſpeak great things of, That he was Grandſon of the famous <hi>Hillel</hi> ſo renowned in their Story, and that at his Death <hi>Onkelos</hi> the Author of the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe ſpent Seventy Pound of Frankincenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Funeral. Such an Education as this, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo great a Doctor, St. <hi>Paul</hi> though would ſufficiently recommend him to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and give him a Character even above the reſt of the Apoſtles, who were all of them beſides Men of an illiterate Education.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe ſhall be to do theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. To ſhew, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> had a peculiar Eminency above the reſt of the Apoſtles.</item>
               <item>II. That the Reaſon of this Eminency was becauſe of his Learned Education.</item>
               <item>III. To urge ſome Chriſtian Exhortations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preſent Occaſion.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60057:5"/>
               <p>I. St. <hi>Paul</hi> had a peculiar Eminency above the reſt of the Apoſtles. Which is obvious to any one who conſiders, 1ſt. How excellently this Apoſtle above the reſt was verſed in the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Learning, how knowing he was in all the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Worſhip of the Moſaical Law, and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their Traditions and Rabbinical Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scripture; as is to be ſeen in all his Epiſtles, particularly that to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where he admirably ſhews the Analogy between the Law and the Goſpel, and, to the Confuſion of the
<hi>Jews,</hi> proves, That their whole Law were but Temporary and Carnal Ordinances, which were only Types and Prefigurations of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices the Death, and the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt, who was to be King and Prieſt for ever. 2. Or if we conſider this great Apoſtle as to his Accompliſhments in Profane and Heathen Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he was far ſuperior to any of the reſt; ſee how he bravely confutes the Idolatry of the
<hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> by a Verſe of <hi>Aratus</hi> one of their own
<hi>Greek</hi> Poets, and ſhews that it muſt be by their own Confeſſion unreaſonable, that the Soul, the <hi>Off-ſpring of God,</hi> ſhould adore a groſs Material Image, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. And how he reprimands thoſe vain Talkers and Deceivers which had got into the Church of <hi>Crete,</hi> by a ſmart Character which <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60057:5"/>
                  <hi>Epimenides</hi> a Poet of that Country had given long before <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>The Cretians are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Lyars, Evil Beaſts, Slow Bellies,</hi> Titus 1.12. 3. Nor was he leſs eminent in deep Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Reaſoning, a judicious ſtating of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Points, and in profitable and preſſing Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to practical Duties. With what ſtrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Arguments does he prove the Call of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the Goſpel, and their non-obligation to the performance of Judaical and aboliſhed Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies? How prudently does he ſtate the Point about Faith and Works? What noble Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms and Sentences do his Epiſtles every where abound with, what cordial Conſolations to the afflicted and perſecuted, what elegant Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the vanity and inconſiderableneſs of this World and the Immortal Joys of the other, what brave encouragements to Perſeverance and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and what paſſionate Exhortations to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity and Unity? How may we obſerve in all his Diſcourſes a particular contempt of Worldly things, and the pious Breathings of a Soul brim full with the Love of God? 4. Nor was he leſs remarkable for his Courage and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Vertues which are particular Qualifications in doubtful and perilous times. What an inſtance of his Chriſtian Bravery and Reſolution was it, <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60057:6"/>to Preach the Goſpel ſo publickly at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where he had ſo many enraged Enemies, when his Friends told him, and he himſelf could not but expect, to be ſacrificed for it? And when the Great St. <hi>Peter</hi> was afraid to diſoblige the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daizing Faction, and was contriving for their ſakes an odd ſort of Comprehenſion or Medly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Judaiſm and Chriſtianity; our brave Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle withſtood him to the Face, and defended the ſimplicity of our Saviour's Religion againſt all the oppoſition of ſo great an Adverſary. 5. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, the indefatigable Labours of his Preaching, and the large Converſions to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity he effected in all Parts almoſt of the <hi>Gentile</hi> World, is enough to raiſe the Honour of him far above the reſt of his Apoſtolick Brethren, whoſe Converſions were in no ways comparable to his. Moſt of the Churches of <hi>Aſia Minor,</hi> thoſe in the Iſlands and Provinces of
<hi>Greece,</hi> thoſe in <hi>Thrace</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> in
<hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> were foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by this ſame St.
<hi>Paul.</hi> And the moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his
<hi>Origines Britannicae</hi> has made it very probable that we of this Nation did receive Chriſtianity likewiſe from this Apoſtle, for the Story of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> is too Modern and too Monkiſh to be credited. And now what a vaſt Tract of Ground is this for this one Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60057:6"/>to ſpread the Goſpel over? How incredible almoſt is it that ſo many different Nations ſhould enjoy the bleſſed Effects of his Miniſtry? for give me leave to ſay that the <hi>Roman</hi> Arms themſelves were hardly more victorious or farther extended than the Plantation of the Goſpel by this one Apoſtle. I come now in the ſecond place to ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>II. That the Reaſon of this Eminency of St. <hi>Paul</hi> was becauſe of his Learned Education.</p>
               <p>And to make out this, I ſhall not tye my ſelf ſtrictly to ſhew how his Learning was the cauſe of thoſe particular Qualifications I have already made appear he was Excellent in, but ſhall ſhew that which will equally prove the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That a Learned Education does beſt qualifie a Man for diſcharging all the Duties which are incumbent on him throughout all the Progreſs of Humane Life, or in any Truſt whatſoever. Now the many and different Characters which belong to Mankind in their diverſe Capacities, may all be reduced to theſe Three.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. As they are Private Men, or Members of Society.</item>
                  <item>2. As they are Magiſtrates or in publick Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</item>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60057:7"/>
                  <item>3. As they are Chriſtians, or Members of God's Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now I ſhall ſhew that a Learned Education does beſt qualifie a Man to diſcharge his Duty in all theſe ſeveral Capacities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>I. A Learned Education does beſt qualifie a Man to diſcharge his Duty as a private Perſon, or Member of Society.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It renders a Man more agreeable in Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood and Converſation. Moſt of your little Animoſities and Quarrels are to be found chiefly amongſt uneducated People; and tho' we find too much of them among Men who have been better bred, yet they are ſeldom guilty of that roughneſs and hard Language which, is common among others: Nay, the obliging and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Airs of Converſation are in the greateſt Heigth and Perfection to he ſeen only in thoſe Gentlemen, who have had the advantage of the moſt Learned Education. For, as for all the other little Arts of Popular Talk and Refin'd Addreſs, they lie but thin ſpread over a Man, like Varniſh, and every untoward Accident makes him lyable to diſcover his inward Imperfections. I will not ſay, that an Education perfectly Bookiſh where Genius, and the Life and Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Nature, and a competent knowledge of <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60057:7"/>the World, are deficient; I will not ſay this does render a Man more agreeable in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but if Men would take care to talk as they ought to do, and would be improving their Minds upon all occaſions, they would find more Satisfaction in the uſeful, tho' unpoliſh'd Diſcourſe, of ſuch a Perſon, than in all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of fine Jeſts and Tales that are requiſite to furniſh out an empty Wit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Learned Education does commonly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow Men with more than ordinary Principles of Generoſity. The Company, which they are Educated among, are Perſons who are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men of Honour, and who value their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and ſcorn a baſe thing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they fall into ſuch Actions they muſt ſort out to themſelves a new Acquaintance; for they will be abandon'd by all their former Friends, who are Lovers of Honour and Vertue. Beſides, their Minds have been habituated to ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Vertues, during their whole Series of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, that they cannot, without a great force upon their Inclinations, ſtoop to ſordid Vices; and a baſe Covetouſneſs, diſhoneſt Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or Treacherouſneſs, and ſuch other ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Vices, and rarely incident to Men of ſuch an Education. Their very Reading in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60057:8"/>and Hiſtory affords them ſuch excellent Rules and Examples which ſo tinctures their Souls with theſe noble Ideas, as makes it no eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them to be tempted to do an unworthy thing. The vulgar and illiterate have very little Senſe of Fame and Honour, and do many ſcandalous things when they may be advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but Men of a Liberal Education have, for the moſt part, ſuch a ſpark of Honour within their Breaſts, as is a guard to them againſt the Commiſſion of any enormous Crimes at leaſt; and oftentimes is the laſt ſtake of Vertue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, when all true Piety and Religion have taken their flight: A ſpark which ſometimes, by God's Grace, kindles again into a bright flame of Piety and true Religion, when others live on ſenſeleſs and ſtupid Sinnners to the laſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Learned Education does render a Man more Eminent in his particular Calling. A Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious knowledge in any part of Literature does qualifie a Man for the underſtanding of any kind of Buſineſs, far better than one who is deſtitute of all. It opens and clears one's Head for a ready preception of whatever ſhall be propoſed to us; for, the more the Mind is uſed to thinking and contemplation, the more quick and perceptive it is, and is diſcernable even in thoſe <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60057:8"/>that have been very little uſed to it. A Lad that has but gone thro' a Form or two in a Grammar-School, that has had Thoughts but a ſmall matter exerciſed about the propriety of Speech, and the congruity of Terms with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, only in the Grammatical way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſhall have a far greater facility in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Art, than one taken from the Plough, or any other who all his time has liv'd by pure Senſe, without any manner of abſtracted Thought or Meditation. But a farther progreſs, in a well managed courſe of Studies, gives a kind of new Genius to the Soul, and oftentimes quickens the ſloweſt Natures; ſo that, when Learning and a noble ſtock of natural Parts meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they muſt needs arrive, in any thing they apply themſelves to, to the utmoſt Perfection that human Nature is capable of. For there is an Analogy between all ſort of Reaſoning, and Men, who have been uſed to make good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences in one Art or Science, with a little Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication may do it as well in another. But I need not go to prove this; for 'tis evident to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones obſervation, that the moſt Famous in any Art whatſoever are generally the beſt Scholars of that Profeſſion. A good Philoſopher and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian ſhall make the beſt Lawyer, and an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60057:9"/>Mathematician an excellent Mechanick; nay by frequently reading ſenſible Authors, a Man will improve his Reaſon ſo that he ſhall be able to Buy and Sell, and manage Trade the better for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>2ly. A Learned Education does beſt qualifie a Man to diſcharge his Duty as a Magiſtrate or in any Publick Capacity; becauſe</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learning gives a Man a greater Knowledge in Publick Affairs. Indeed a General ought not to be made of a Cowardly Scholar, but if the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral have Learning and Courage too, he is much the fitter for that Employ; for there is a great deal more in ſuch a Truſt than bear Fighting and Killing; and a complete Knowledge in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory which is the Experience of many Ages, is as much requiſite as making Campaigns. Nay, the greateſt Generals in the World were Men of Learning. <hi>Alexander</hi> ſtudied and converſed with Philoſophers all the while he was Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the
<hi>Perſian</hi> Empire: And <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> was as good a Writer as he was a Soldier. And ſo likewiſe as for Civil Truſts, though of late Years the Characters of Bookiſh and Pedantical have excluded a great many worthy Men from Publick Buſineſs, yet it is well known that, in our Forefathers time, Buſineſs was as well done <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60057:9"/>when ſuch Men, as they characteriſe by thoſe Names, were in Power. But why ſhould a Man make a Politician, when he could not make a Scholar? Certainly there are as much Brains and Diligence required, to be able to Govern and Direct the Affairs of a Nation, as there is to underſtand a Greek or Latin Book; and he, that was never able to attain to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will find the former a little too hard. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it may ſometimes happen that a Man of an extraordinary ſtock of Nature, though defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in Learning, may be a conſiderable Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but if that Man had had the advantage of Literature too, he would have done Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in ſuch a Poſt. For we have Inſtances what great things Learning alone has done in ſuch Stations together with heavy Parts; then what muſt it have produced, in conjunction with a noble Genius, and all the ſprightly force of Nature? For ſuch a one ſhall not only have the quickneſs and ſagacity to diſcover the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of an Enemy, but ſhall have before him in his mind all the old Plots and Contrivances of former Princes and States againſt each other, and know how they have ſucceeded, or how they were prevented; what good or ill Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents have furthered or retarded Sieges or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions, <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60057:10"/>and may be in probability of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening ſtill; what have been the Methods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the riſe of the greateſt Governments, and what has been the occaſion of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay; what has been the omiſſion of Princes to ſuffer the exorbitant growth of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or to breed Tumults or Seditions at Home; what Land or Naval Forces are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the ſituation or circumſtances of a Nation; what Taxes are leaſt oppreſſive, lie more equally upon a People are beſt proportion'd to their Wealth and Trade, and are more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Inclinations; People in ſhort, by comparing their own with Antient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Governments, ſhall know wherein the true Intereſt and Welfare of the Nation does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Theſe are Qualifications which are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary for a good Stateſman, and yet are not to be attained but by an diligent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Thought and by hard Study; but I am ſure they are never to be got only by living within the Walls of a Court, by pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up News and attending at the Levies, and what is worſe by Flattery and Diſſimulation, by betraying and undermining their beſt Friends; which has been the modern Method of training a Politician.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60057:10"/>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe Men of Learning are commonly more ſincere and faithful in Publick Employs than others. Such Men for the moſt part have lived more ſober and vertuous Lives; for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpent their Youth in ſevere Study, they could not be guilty of thoſe mad Exceſſes, which the illiterate Gentlemen uſually lay out their Time in, and which gives them oftentimes ſuch a vile Character in the Opinion of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. The firſt of theſe when they are hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a Publick Employ they dare not ſtain that good Reputation, the World has beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them, by any foul Practices; whilſt the other Gentlemen, who by their Intemperate and Rakiſh Lives have made their Character ſo wretched and deſpicable, are prompted to think that even Corruption can hardly make it worſe. The former, beſides their Learning, have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally laſting Principles of Vertue in them, which will direct them in all Stations; whilſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though they leave off their ſcandalous irregularities, are either Vertuous through im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence or cautiouſly Vicious; or, though they are arrived to an Age when ſenſuality is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to them, yet then the Devil has ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet of Baits to tempt them with, and their Minds ſhall be liable to all the Corruption and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60057:11"/>indirect Practices which Covetouſneſs, the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Vice of an unregenerate Old Age, ſhall put them upon. I do not ſay that all Stateſmen who have not the advantage of Learning are corrupt, or that there are no Wiſe and Good Men, who have ſpent their Youth fooliſhly and extravagantly; but this I ſay, and I think upon good grounds, that if care was taken, that the moſt conſiderable Stations in the Government were filled by Men of a competency in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and of a ſerious and ſober Life, there would be much leſs reaſon to complain of Evil Counſellors and Publick Miſcarriages, than when Men are ſuffered to get into theſe Poſts with no other Qualifications, than the recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of great Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>3ly. A Learned Education doth beſt qualifie a Man to diſcharge his Duty as a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſuch Men have a more Perfect Knowledge of all the Duties and Obligations which are incumbent on them. God complains thus of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Hoſ. 4.6. <hi>My People are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for lack of Knowledge.</hi> A great many Men are eternally ruin'd for want of due. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction at firſt in the Principles of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſome miſcarry by having their Thoughts totally bent upon ſuch Worldly Callings as give <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60057:11"/>them but little leaſure to reflect upon a better State; and laſtly, others fall <hi>into dangerous Sins often</hi> upon account of Ignorance and for want of underſtanding the Meaſures of their Duty. But a literate Education provides againſt all theſe things. Men that have had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this are well principled from their Childhood in Chriſtian Duties; they are uſually bred to more generous Employs, which afford them more frequent converſation with the beſt and moſt learned Men, and more opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Reading and Devotion; they have uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch a Knowledge in the Holy Scriptures, and in all points of their Duty, that they themſelves are able to ſettle in their own thoughts the boundaries of Vertue and Vice, and upon this account are not ſo liable to commit Sin through Ignorance or Miſtake.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe ſuch Men are not ſo liable to be led away by ill Examples.</p>
               <p>The uneducated part of Mankind live only by example, and (like Cattle) unthinkingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after thoſe that go before them, and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Generality of the World have little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Religion, or are lewd and debauched, they are ſo too. But Men of a literate Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do better conſider matters, and look into the Reaſons of things; they ſee it is unreaſonable and <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60057:12"/>fooliſh, to looſe their Religion, for a Faſhion; or to forfeit their Intereſt with God, to imitate the Vices of ſome admired Great Man. Theſe Mens Reaſons are too ſtrong, and their Souls too brave to be guilty of ſuch ſordid and fooliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe ſuch Men have a more Rational and noble ſenſe of Religion.</p>
               <p>The Vulgar, for the moſt part, take up their Religion upon Truſt, as a certain Property be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their Country or their Family; which they have a veneration for, becauſe thoſe Perſons, they have a great Opinion of, have the like; and which they muſt in ſome meaſure comply with, or they ſhall appear ſingular or give offence to thoſe, they are not willing to diſoblige. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that are better inſtructed practice the Rules of Chriſtianity, as unqueſtionable Truths deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them by their Parents, and inculcated to them by their Paſtors. And I doubt not but Men may be ſaved, if they be ſincerely Religious and fulfill our Saviours Commands, upon theſe Grounds. But then no one can deny, but that they have a more rational Ground of their Faith, and a nobler ſenſe of Religion, who having lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and learning have examined all the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſtianity, who are fully ſatisfied that our Saviour and his Apoſtles Preached all thoſe <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60057:12"/>Doctrines, and did all thoſe Miracles they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to have done in confirmation of them, and are ſure that Chriſtianity can be no Dream or Impoſture of Deſigning or Enthuſiaſtical Men, but that it is the moſt Heavenly and the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Inſtitution which ever was in the World. The former do obey our Saviours Laws only as neceſſary Duties, but theſe readily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them as a reaſonable ſervice. They are brought to their Duties by the compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Hopes and Fears, by the Command or Example of Superiors, or by warm and affectionate Diſcourſes; whilſt Theſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace our Saviours Doctrines, becauſe they ſo admirably fall in with the Dictates of right Reaſon, and are worthy of God the Author of them, and becauſe they have all the reaſon in the World to think, that God Almighty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them. The firſt breeds for the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality only an Awful Fear of God; but the other makes Men approach him with a hearty and generous Love. They may be true Believers, but then they are often liable to be ſhock'd by every captious Atheiſtical Objection; whilſt Theſe have ſcand over all the ſpecious Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Infidels againſt our Religion, and notwithſtanding this they do adore and hope in Crucified Jeſus, in the midſt of all the loud <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60057:13"/>Blaſphemies of an Incredulous Age. Theſe are the advantages which we have by a Learned Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our ſeveral Capacities, as we are <hi>Men in a Society,</hi> or <hi>Governors,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> to which we may add another advantage, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Inward Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to our ſelves,</hi> the pleaſure of reading ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble and raviſhing Authors, and to ſpend our time ſo agreeably, whilſt that of others hangs ſo uncomfortably upon their Hands; the inexpreſſible Delight of having our knowledge daily improved by being let into ſo many uſeful and entertaining Truths; to dive into the hidden ſecrets of Nature by
<hi>Philoſophy,</hi> to run back and converſe with all the former Ages by
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> to underſtand the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and to reconcile the Differences in God's Word by <hi>Theology,</hi> and to determine the meaſures of Right and Wrong, and exactly to lay out the Lines of Juſtice and Equity by a Knowledge in the Laws: theſe are ſuch delightſome qualifications, as when they are not ſoured accidentally by Pride or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, but poſſeſſed together with Modeſty and a Peaceable Diſpoſition, if there be any happineſs in this World, this is certainly one of the greateſt on this ſide Heaven. I now come to the third and laſt things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>III. To urge ſome Chriſtian Exhortations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preſent Occaſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And firſt my Chriſtian Brethren, you my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60057:13"/>Deareſt Companions of my tender Years, You with whom I had the happineſs, to lay the Foundation of my Studies in the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing School, where we have gain'd the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of ſuch an Education, as has improved our Minds beyond the generality of thoſe who have unhappily been deſtitute of the like noble Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; let me exhort you all to pay your hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thanks to God the Giver of every good Gift, for the great advantage of this Education, and when in your Praiſes to God you recount the many great Benefits he conferred upon you to remember this as one of the moſt conſiderable. And now we have a happy opportunity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it together in Publick, eſpecially at this time in this place, which bear a particular relation to our School and Founder. Methinks I ſee darting through all our Soulr a ſecret and unexpreſſible pleaſure to think, that we ſhould ſo luckily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new this our Antient Love Feaſt upon the firſt Anniverſary of this bleſſed Saint, after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building of his Temple; and now we are grown Men, that we can devoutly meet together and Praiſe God in this Glorious Edifice, where we remember to have play'd our Childiſh Paſtimes among its deſolate Ruins.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us pay our utmoſt gratitude towards the Place and Preceptors of our Education. Let us do our utmoſt to encourage and befriend this <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60057:14"/>Foundation, and to make it Flouriſh as much as we can; that it may be as advantageous to Thouſands more in future Times as it has been to us. Let us always bear the greateſt Reſpect and Veneration to thoſe Worthy Perſons by whoſe Care and Learning we had our Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. To be Bred under a good School-maſter is a laſting Bleſſing as long as we live, as an Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation under a bad one is a lamentable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrievable Misfortune; and though a Man may notwithſtanding this Diſadvantage be ſomewhat conſiderable, yet he is like a Houſe built upon a falſe Foundation always weak and tottering. Therefore Great Publick Schools, where Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Learning is in its higheſt Perfection, can never enough be eſteemed and encouraged, and the Maſters honoured and rever'd by their Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who have received ſuch an ineſtimable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from them: From them who have been ſo kind to us to afford us all the pleaſures and ſatisfactions of that Learning they have impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in us, and to be content with the Toil and Drudgery of it themſelves; who have been pleas'd to forego the more agreeable Employments to do a more Publick Good, and to ſpend their time in a laborious and what is worſe a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Calling, when the Injuſtice and the Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Age is ſuch, that they are conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blamed for every Miſcarriage, and hardly thanked for any Succeſs.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60057:14"/>
               <p n="2">2. Let us all unite together in a ſtrict Bond of Love and Friendſhip, to each other. Let us remember thoſe mutual Endearments which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between us in thoſe early Years, and again let us renew our Affections in a maturer Age, if abſence and diſcontinuance from one another has abated them. Theſe early Friendſhips of all others are the beſt and the ſtrongeſt. The fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarities which Men fall into afterwards are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally but the forming of Deſigns or courting an Intereſt; and if theſe fail ſo does their Friendſhip too. But in that tender Age pure natural Simplicity, and Love without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion governs the Affections; and we enter then into the choiceſt familiarity only with them, whoſe Souls we find more tuneable and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with ours. And why ſhould we not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſame Friendſhips ſtill, which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at a time when Nature lay open and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſguiſed; rather than to maintain a familiarity chiefly with thoſe whom it may be only Craft or Deſign obliges to be faithful. Beſides, a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Friendſhip among our ſelves has a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand advantages attending it, wherein we may be ſerviceable to one another; the Profeſſion of one may be beneficial to that of another, and the application of many of ſuch a Society may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Kindneſs for a ſingle Perſon, which he could not procure himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60057:15"/>
               <p n="4">4. Let us all endeavour, that our good Lives may be anſwerable to the Education, which has been given us. Let us always bear in mind that of our Saviour, <hi>He that knoweth his Maſters Will and doth it not ſhall be beaten with many Stripes.</hi> God expects we ſhould live better than the illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Vulgar who have leſs Knowledge, and that our good Lives ſhould be an example to them to copy from. But if we allow our ſelves in ſhameful and beaſtly Vices, not only the Rules of our Holy Religion, but the very Verſes and Sentences of our Heathen Claſſicks will make our Conſciences and fly in our Faces. But I hope we ſhall all make that good improvement of our Time and Education, <hi>as to work out our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with fear and trembling, and to let our light ſhine before Men that they may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven,</hi> that we ſhall live in the fear of God, in Chriſtian Charity with all Men, and a hearty Friendſhip among our ſelves as long as God ſhall be pleaſed to continue us in this World, and that we may all of us be happy in the next, and that at the Reſurrection of the Juſt, we may all meet again at the Great Marriage Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lamb, when we ſhall be join'd to the bleſſed Community of the Saints and we ſhall live and enjoy and Love for ever. <hi>Which God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60057:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
